<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Primitive baptism, and therein infants and parents rights</title>
            <author>Sylvester, Matthew, 1636 or 7-1708.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1690</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 64 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 22 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A62091</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S6332</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R220779</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99832170</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99832170</idno>
            <idno type="VID">36641</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A62091)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 36641)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2136:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Primitive baptism, and therein infants and parents rights</title>
                  <author>Sylvester, Matthew, 1636 or 7-1708.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>36, [4] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Jonathan Robinson, at the Golden-Lion in St. Paul's Church-Yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDCXC. [1690]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"To the reader" is signed: M. Sylvester.</note>
                  <note>Includes appendix, and a final leaf of advertisements.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Baptism --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Infant baptism --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Amanda Flynn</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Amanda Flynn</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:36641:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>PRIMITIVE BAPTISM, And therein INFANTS AND PARENTS RIGHT.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>MATTH. 19.6.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>What God hath joined together, let no Man put aſunder.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Ionathan Robinſon,</hi> at the Golden-Lion in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-Yard, MDCXC.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:36641:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:36641:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:36641:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:36641:3"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>THE Author of theſe Papers is one whom I have known long ſince to be a perſon of great Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation for Knowledg, Wiſdom, Gravity and Seriouſneſs. A Perſon not only skil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and diligent in his particular Calling, and beautiful in his Chriſtian Converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but alſo a diligent and judicious Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and Obſerver of the Sacred Scriptures; and, ſo far as I could either learn of others, or my ſelf diſcern by Converſation with him, an impartial ſearcher after Truth, and readily receptive of it in its diſcerned Evidence: and conſequently not tenacious of any Sentiments or Opinions through humour, intereſt, and ſelf-conceitedneſs where
<pb facs="tcp:36641:4"/> any reaſons do appear to prove them falſe, or probably uncertain or unſafe. That this ſmall <hi>Tract</hi> is his, I have great reaſon to believe: It is ſmall, nervous, and clear, as to the great Deſign thereof; of which, the <hi>Title</hi> is a ſufficient indication and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count; but let the matter ſpeak for it ſelf, and force its way into the Readers breaſt by its own Strength, carried home by God's bleſſing thereupon to ſuch degrees as He ſees fit, who is the Original ſource and Fountain, Patron, and End of Truth. I ſhall only add, That when our Brethren who judg it <hi>improbable,</hi> that <hi>any In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants had their ſolemn admiſſion in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Church of Chriſt in Scripture-times by the inſtituted rite of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Baptiſm,</hi> have tryed their Strength upon what is here offer'd, and ſcripturally proved, and have effectually Anſwered what is <hi>here briefly,</hi> and in other Books, more <hi>copiouſly</hi> demonſtrated and impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, they may probably gain more Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelytes
<pb facs="tcp:36641:4"/> to themſelves. Read carefully, think deeply, pray fervently, deſign ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly, judg impartially, and give Chriſt's evident Truths, Laws, Inſtitutions, their juſt receptions and improvement; and take in nothing for Truth or Duty for the ſake of any Man, but yield to Evidence; and this will be moſt grateful,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>(Candid and Chriſtian Reader,) To thine in and for our Bleſſed Lord, whilſt M. SYLVESTER.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:36641:5"/>
            <head>PREFACE.</head>
            <p>AS Civil Right is one of the great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverted Points in the World; ſo is Religious Right in the Church.</p>
            <p>What is here offered concerning Infants and Parents Right in the Church, is a ſhort Diſcourſe maintained againſt two different Practices; the One withholding Baptiſm from Infants of baptized Parents; the Other withholding ſuch Parents from their Infants in Baptiſm.</p>
            <p>The Arguments brought againſt theſe Practices, are thoſe brought by Chriſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt a Practice of the like Nature, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that it is a putting aſunder thoſe whom God hath joined together; and that from the beginning it was not ſo.</p>
            <p>Which Arguments are not inſiſted upon as ſuſpecting the ſtrength of other Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, but as agreeing therewith, and the better to clear up the Apoſtolical Practice in theſe things.</p>
            <p>All ſubmitted to ſuperior Judgments.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:36641:5"/>
            <head>Primitive Baptiſm.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>GOD who at ſundry times, and in divers manners, ſpake in times paſt unto the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers by the Prophets, hath in theſe laſt days ſpoken to us by his Son:</hi> Who (that our Religion and Manners, Faith and Worſhip, may be after the due Order) hath commanded us <hi>to ſearch the Scriptures,</hi> containing Rules and Directions, Precepts and Examples, always evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent and perfect in their kind, though not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways alike expreſs.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Sadduces</hi> finding no expreſs mention of the Reſurrection in the Books of <hi>Moſes,</hi> (which they emphatically called the <hi>Scriptures</hi>) not only denied the Reſurrection, but framed Arguments from thoſe Scriptures againſt it; One whereof they thought ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anſwerable,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 25.6.</note> that they encountred Chriſt himſelf with it, <hi>Mat.</hi> 22. <hi>v.</hi> 23, 24, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Chriſt obſerving their Confidence, reproves them as plainly both of Error, and the Cauſe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, in theſe Words, <hi>ver.</hi> 29. <hi>Ye do err, not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Scriptures, nor the Power of God;</hi> and from the Scriptures proves the Reſurrection.</p>
            <p>Which Words of Chriſt, <hi>Ye do err, not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Scriptures, nor the Power of God,</hi> may have a double Aſpect, one unto the Scripture, from whence they framed their Argument againſt the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:36641:6"/> Reſurrection, and another unto the Scripture which he brings to prove the Reſurrection by.</p>
            <p>That the <hi>Sadduces</hi> did not know the Scriptures literally, or the Power of God hiſtorically, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be the meaning of Chriſt; but take the Words as having an Eye to that Scripture brought by them, (<hi>ver.</hi> 24.) from whence they raiſed their Argument againſt the Reſurrection, and the Senſe may be ſuch as this:</p>
            <p>Ye <hi>Sadduces</hi> ſay that there is no Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and you ſeem very big of your Opinion, as if you were in the right, and had Scripture on your ſide, and could from the Scripture prove it impoſſible; but I tell you, <hi>Ye err, not knowing the Scriptures, nor the Power of God;</hi> for though that be Scripture which ye have quoted, yet ye, not comparing it with other Paſſages of the ſame Sacred Writings, nor Spiritual Things with Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual, do not hold the Analogy of Faith con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in the Scriptures, but ſpeak evil of thoſe things which ye know not, whilſt what you know naturally as brute Beaſts, in thoſe things you corrupt your ſelves. For that the Dead are raiſed, even <hi>Moſes</hi> ſhewed at the Buſh, when he calleth the Lord the God of <hi>Abraham,</hi> and the God of <hi>Iſaac,</hi> and the God of <hi>Jacob,</hi> for he is not the God of the Dead, but of the Living, for all live unto him. And though you pretend to know God, yet you glorify him not as God, nor conſider that Power belongs unto him, elſe why ſhould it be thought a thing incredible with you, that God ſhould raiſe the Dead? Neither are your Notions of the future State, to which the Dead are raiſed by his Infinite and Almighty
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:36641:6"/> power, ſuitable to thoſe high and excellent Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions which you ought to have of it, for in the Reſurrection they neither marry, nor are given in Marriage, neither do they die any more, but are as the Angels of God in Heaven. Ye therefore do greatly err.</p>
            <p>But taking the Words of Chriſt, as having a reſpect to the Scripture which he brings to prove the Reſurrection by, (<hi>ver.</hi> 32.) and then the meaning may be this, or ſuch like:</p>
            <p>Ye deny that there is any Reſurrection, and conclude that you muſt be in the right, becauſe you find no expreſs mention of it in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and as if the Incapacity of the Dead made it impoſſible with God; but do you not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore err, becauſe you know not the Scriptures, nor the Power of God? For though it be not expreſly ſaid that the Dead are raiſed, yet know that there is ſufficient Proof for it in Scripture, by good and warrantable Inference from Scripture: For as touching the Reſurrection of the Dead, have you not read that which was ſpoken to you by God, ſaying, I am the God of <hi>Abraham,</hi> and the God of <hi>Iſaac,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 22.31.</note> and the God of <hi>Jacob?</hi> from whence you might have attained unto the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg of the Reſurrection as ſatisfyingly, as if it had been expreſly ſaid, that the Dead are rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed; for God is not a God of the Dead, but of the Living: which had you conſidered, you might have known that the Spirits of Men, though ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate from their Bodies, are by the Power of God, <hi>(the God of the Spirits of all Fleſh)</hi> ſtill held in Life; and that therefore he can and will
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:36641:7"/> by the ſame Power, according to the working, whereby he is able to ſubdue all things to himſelf, raiſe their Bodies, and unite them to their own Spirits: which Inferences being agreeable to the Holy Scriptures, and a true and right aſſerting of the Power of God, are <hi>as Scripture,</hi> of which ye being willingly or wilfully ignorant, have er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in this main Article.</p>
            <p>Now though the <hi>Sadduces</hi> ſtill perſiſted, after ſuch Conviction, in their Error, ſaying that <hi>there is no Reſurrection,</hi> and in oppoſition to the Doctrine of Chriſt, <hi>Luke</hi> 20.37, 38. that <hi>there is neither Angel nor Spirit,</hi> yet the way of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving by Conſequences is not leſs cogent or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable.</p>
            <p>And if the Reſurrection might be thus pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, why not other Points? why not the bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing of Infants?</p>
            <p>It is true, the Reſurrection is not Worſhip, yet it is an Article of Faith, which if not believed,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.13, 14, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> all our Worſhip is in vain: And though nothing is to be admitted into the Worſhip of God, as ſuch, which is contrary to expreſs Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept and Command by Conſequences, yet theſe rightly drawn from Scripture, are no leſs a Rule for our Practice, than they are for our Faith.</p>
            <p>Now tho the baptizing of Infants hath been a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundantly proved from time to time by many plain and undeniable Conſequences, rightly infer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red from the Scriptures, which being Chriſt's way of proving, ſhould ſatisfy us; yet ſince expreſs Precept or Example are ſo much called for, let us a little enquire into that.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:36641:7"/>
            <p>What the Firſt Commiſſion of Chriſt was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout baptizing, is not recorded, but muſt be ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered from his Second Commiſſion, and from the Practice of his Diſciples, and Acts of the Apoſtles.</p>
            <p>The Second Commiſſion of Chriſt for bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing, is <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.19. <hi>Go ye therefore, and teach all Nations, baptizing them in the Name of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and of the Son, and of the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>The Practice of the Diſciples and Apoſtles was to baptize particular Perſons, and with Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents their Houſe and Houſhold; as <hi>Lydia</hi> and all her Houſhold, <hi>Acts</hi> 16.14, 15. the Jailor and all his, <hi>ver.</hi> 33. and <hi>Criſpus</hi> and all his Houſe, <hi>Chap.</hi> 18.8.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt.</hi> The Queſtion is, Whether theſe were only Adult, or Adult and Infants?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Adult and Infants. Theſe words, <hi>Houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, His,</hi> and <hi>Houſe,</hi> when ſpoken of Perſons, being an Hebraiſm for <hi>Children of the Houſe,</hi> who are the Seed of the Houſe,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.33.</note> 
               <hi>Deut.</hi> 25.5. <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.12, 19. whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they be Infants or adult Children.</p>
            <p>Thus <hi>Gen.</hi> 34.30. <hi>I and my Houſe;</hi> and 41.13, 19. <hi>Pharaoh</hi> ſaid, <hi>Take your Father, and your little ones, and your Wives, and come;</hi> and 46.31. <hi>My Brethren, and my Father's Houſe are come. Numb.</hi> 16.32. <hi>And the Earth opened her Mouth, and ſwallowed them up, and their Houſes,</hi> that is, their Sons and little Children, <hi>ver.</hi> 27. to wit, of <hi>Dathan</hi> and <hi>Abiram,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 11.6.</note> whereas of <hi>Korah</hi> it was all the Men that appertained unto him, as in the ſame 32d Verſe, not his Houſe, for <hi>chap.</hi> 26.11. the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:36641:8"/> Children of <hi>Korah</hi> died not: <hi>Judg.</hi> 9.16. <hi>Now therefore if ye have done truly—and dealt well with</hi> Jerubbaal <hi>and his Houſe: (for my Father fought for you,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and ye are riſen up againſt my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther's Houſe, and have ſlain his Sons) If ye have dealt truly and ſincerely with</hi> Jerubbaal <hi>and his Houſe, then rejoice,</hi> &amp;c. 1 Sam. 3.12, 13, 14. <hi>In that day I will perform againſt</hi> Eli <hi>all which I have ſpoken concerning his Houſe,</hi> &amp;c. 2 Sam. 3.1, 6. <hi>Now there was long War betwixt the Houſe of</hi> Saul, <hi>and the Houſe of</hi> David, &amp;c. And chap. 7.16, 18, 19, 23, 29. <hi>Thine Houſe ſhall be eſtabliſhed,</hi> &amp;c. And chap. 9.3. <hi>And the King ſaid, Is there not yet any of the Houſe of</hi> Saul? And chap. 12.10. <hi>Now the Sword ſhall not depart from thy Houſe.</hi> 1 Kings 13.34. <hi>And this thing became Sin to the Houſe of</hi> Jeroboam. And chap. 21.21, 22. <hi>And will take away thy Poſterity;— And will make thy Houſe like the Houſe of</hi> Jeroboam. 1 Chron. 13.14. <hi>The Lord bleſſed the Houſe of</hi> Obed Edom; (that is, <hi>chap.</hi> 26.4, 5, 6. <hi>his Children.</hi>) And chap. 1.16, 43. David <hi>returned to bleſs his Houſe.</hi> Pſal. 114.1. <hi>When</hi> Iſrael <hi>went out of</hi> Egypt, <hi>the Houſe of</hi> Jacob <hi>from a People of a ſtrange Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage.</hi> Micah 2.2. <hi>They oppreſs a Man and his Houſe.</hi> Habbak. 2.10.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jer.</hi> 23.34.</note> 
               <hi>Thou haſt conſulted Shame to thine Houſe.</hi> Luke 19.9. <hi>This day is Salvation come to this Houſe.</hi> Titus 1.11. <hi>Who ſubvert whole Houſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Add unto theſe Gen. 7.1. <hi>And the Lord ſaid unto</hi> Noah, <hi>Come thou, and all thy Houſe.</hi> So chap. 18.19. <hi>I know</hi> Abraham, <hi>that he will com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand his Children, and Houſhold after him</hi> (that
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:36641:8"/> is, his Children who are his <hi>Houſhold</hi> after him; for no others of the Family, tho' it exclude not them, were properly his <hi>Houſhold</hi> after him, but his Children, called his <hi>Seed</hi> after him.) Thus <hi>ch.</hi> 30.30. <hi>And now when ſhall I</hi> (ſays <hi>Jacob) provide for mine own Houſe alſo?</hi> So <hi>Exod.</hi> 12.27. <hi>It is the Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of the Lord's Paſſover, who paſſed over the Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of the children of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>when he ſmote the</hi> Aegyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians, <hi>and delivered our Houſes.</hi> Thus <hi>Deut.</hi> 25.9. <hi>So ſhall it be done unto the man that will not build up his brother's houſe.</hi> So 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. <hi>v.</hi> 4, 5. <hi>One that rules well his own houſe, having his children in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection with all gravity: for if a man know not how to rule his own houſe, how ſhall he take care of the Church of God?</hi> And <hi>Chap.</hi> 5.8. <hi>But if any pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide not for his own, and eſpecially for thoſe of his own Houſe,</hi> which according to the ſame Apoſtle, 2 Cor. 12.14. is his Children, <hi>For the Children ought not to lay up for the Parents, but the Parents for the Children.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus we ſee the Hebraiſm of theſe Words; <hi>Houſhold, His,</hi> and <hi>Houſe in Scripture,</hi> according un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to which theſe Words in theſe three firſt cited Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of <hi>Lydia,</hi> the <hi>Jaylor</hi> and <hi>Criſpus,</hi> are by ſome very great Interpreters rendred, <hi>The Children of the Houſe;</hi> and are neceſſarily to be ſo taken there, Infants not excepted, unleſs ſome ſufficient rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon be given to the contrary.</p>
            <p>Now the main Reaſon to the contrary given, is, That theſe <hi>Houſes</hi> and <hi>Houſholds</hi> who are ſaid to be Baptized, were ſuch as to whom the Word of the Lord is ſaid to be ſpoken, and who are ſaid to believe in the Lord, which it is pretended they could not do if ſpoken of Infants; ſo that there were either
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:36641:9"/> no Infants there, or no Infants there Bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed.</p>
            <p>But this Reaſon is not ſufficient, becauſe it ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth theſe <hi>Houſes</hi> and <hi>Houſholds</hi> to be ſaid to have the Word of the Lord ſpoken to them, and to be ſaid to Believe without the Parents, which ought not to be ſuppoſed.</p>
            <p>Firſt, it ſuppoſes theſe <hi>Houſes</hi> and <hi>Houſholds</hi> to be ſaid to have the Word of the Lord ſpoken to them without the Parents, and ſo renders Infants incapa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; whereas, take <hi>Houſe</hi> and <hi>Houſhold</hi> with <hi>Parents,</hi> and <hi>Infants</hi> have been, and ſo may be, of them to whom the Word of the Lord hath been ſpoken. Thus Children were of them to whom <hi>Moſes</hi> made that great and ſolemn Exhortation <hi>Deut.</hi> 29.2, 9, 10, 11. <hi>And Moſes call'd unto all Iſrael, and ſaid unto them,—Keep therefore the word of this Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant—.Ye ſtand all of you before the Lord your God,—your little Ones, your Wives,—that ye ſhould enter into Covenant with the Lord thy God, and into his Oath, which the Lord thy God maketh with thee this day.</hi> And of them to whom <hi>Joſhua</hi> made that famous repetition of the Law, <hi>Joſh.</hi> 8.34, 35. <hi>And afterwards he read all the words of the Law, the bleſſings and curſings according to all that is written in the book of the Law. There was not a word of all that</hi> Moſes <hi>commanded, which</hi> Joſhuah <hi>read not before all the Congregation of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>with the Women and little Ones.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And tho' it be ſaid in <hi>Nehem.</hi> 8.2, 3. <hi>Men and Women, and all that could hear with underſtanding,</hi> yet it is not ſaid them only, as if Infants were ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted, neither doth it follow that they were; for we know that whatſoever the Law ſaith, it ſaith to
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:36641:9"/> them that are under the Law, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.19. And we are ſure, that the Command of <hi>Moſes, Deut.</hi> 31.11, 12, 13. was, that the Solemnity there appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, ſhould be with the Women and Children. Alſo, when he call'd unto all <hi>Iſrael, Deut.</hi> 29. aforeſaid, and made that Exhortation, <hi>They ſtood be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him with their little Ones, and their Wives.</hi> Likewiſe, when <hi>Joſhua</hi> made that Rehearſal of the Law, <hi>Chap.</hi> 8. <hi>It was before the whole Congregation, with the Women and little Ones.</hi> So 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 20.13. <hi>And all</hi> Iſrael <hi>ſtood before the Lord with their little Ones, their Wives and their Children.</hi> Still Women with their little Ones and Children, as if ſuch little Ones, as by reaſon of their Infancy did yet hang upon the tender Breaſt: agreeable unto that <hi>Joel</hi> 2.12. <hi>Turn ye unto me—with weeping and mourning:</hi> 13. <hi>rent your hearts,</hi>— 15. <hi>Call a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn Aſſembly.</hi> —16. <hi>Gather the People: ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy the Congregation: aſſemble the Elders: gather the Children, and thoſe that ſuck the Breaſt,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Not that Parents ought therefore to bring their little Ones at all times to the reading, and preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Word; but ſhews that it was done upon ſome great and ſolemn Occaſions, when they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into Covenant with God, or the like; and that <hi>little Ones</hi> may be part of thoſe to whom the Word of the Lord is ſpoken, <hi>Act.</hi> 21.5.</p>
            <p>It is granted, the Phraſe and manner of ſpeaking in Scripture is primarily accommodated to thoſe who are adult, but not excluſively of Infants; for they, as <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> were of them to whom, ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>appertaineth the giving of the Law,</hi> Rom. 3.19. And, as Jews, <hi>of them to whom were committed the Oracles of God,</hi> Rom. 3.1, 2. Acts 7.38.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:36641:10"/>
            <p>Secondly, this ſuppoſeth theſe <hi>Houſes</hi> and <hi>Houſholds</hi> to be ſaid to Believe without the Parents, and ſo though it had inſtead of <hi>Houſe</hi> and <hi>Houſhold,</hi> been ſaid, <hi>their Children, little Ones,</hi> and <hi>Babes;</hi> yet ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to this ſuppoſal the meaning would have been made ſtill the ſame; that this could not be of ſuch in Age, but onely of ſuch in quality and diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition; whereas, take it as it is, <hi>Parents</hi> and <hi>Houſe</hi> together, and then <hi>Infants</hi> are not onely included, but chiefly intended, the Adult being for the moſt part at their own diſpoſal, whilſt the Infants were al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways at the diſpoſal of their Parents, who them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, whether <hi>Heathens,</hi> or <hi>Jews,</hi> being converted to the Faith of Chriſt, brought over theirs, all if poſſible, but be ſure their Infants, to be of the ſame Faith with themſelves; and it being Parent and Houſe, and not Houſe without the Parents, who are ſaid to Believe; it ſhews it to be in a way of Covenant, which always includes the Infants: And thus as the Infants of <hi>Heathens</hi> were always repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to be <hi>Heathens,</hi> and the Infants of <hi>Jews</hi> to be <hi>Jews,</hi> ſo the Infants of <hi>Chriſtians</hi> to be <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> (tho' not declaratively ſo, no more than the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted Adult until baptized) and may, as Infants of ſuch,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.6. <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.10. <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.19.</note> as well be ſaid to Believe, as the Infants of Circumciſed Parents might be ſaid, by being Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed, to become debtors to do the whole Law, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.2. Or, by not being Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed, to break the Covenant, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.14.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> But it is ſaid, <hi>Faith comes by hearing, Rom.</hi> 10.17. How then can Infants be ſaid to Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> This goes upon the former miſtake of
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:36641:10"/> putting Parents and Infants aſunder, for ſo it is ſaid, <hi>He that believeth not, ſhall be damned.</hi> Mark 16.16. <hi>and is condemned already,</hi> John 3.18. Shall not Infants therefore be ſaved? God forbid, for tho they cannot believe in all reſpects as the Adult do, yet they may be parties with their Parents in the covenanting part of their Parents Faith, as their Parents covenant for themſelves and them; which is well illuſtrated by Parents making their Infants Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties with them in their own civil Contracts of Bonds and Leaſes, but is grounded only upon the Nature of the Covenant of God; and as this Faith comes to the Parents by hearing, ſo to their Infants in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction with them.</p>
            <p>When therefore it is ſaid ſuch and ſuch, as Name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the <hi>Jailor, Criſpus,</hi> and the <hi>Nobleman,</hi> John 4.53. <hi>believed with all their Houſe:</hi> this relates not ſo much to the great ſucceſs the Goſpel had in thoſe times, tho' that was very great, as it doth to the Covenant of God with Parents and their Children; becauſe no <hi>Houſe</hi> is ſaid to believe without the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, nor any Parents having <hi>Houſe</hi> under their charge, without the <hi>Houſe;</hi> which muſt therefore have a reſpect to Infants, Adult Perſons ſometimes believing, and not their Parents; and Parents, and not always the Adult.</p>
            <p>An Husband might believe, and not the Wife; the Wife, and not the Husband: but tho' it be ſaid, to a Husband, or a Wife, <hi>Believe, and thou ſhalt be ſaved, and thy Houſe;</hi> yet it is not ſaid to any Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, <hi>Believe, and thou ſhalt be ſaved, and thy Wife;</hi> or to any Wife, <hi>Believe, and thou ſhalt be ſaved, and thy Husband;</hi> but only, <hi>What knoweſt thou O Wife, whether thou ſhalt ſave thy Husband? Or, how know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:36641:11"/> thou, O man, whether thou ſhalt ſave thy Wife?</hi> 1 Cor. 7.16.</p>
            <p>Again, a Maſter might be Converted, and not the Servant; a Servant might be Called, and not the Maſter; but with conſiderable difference in reſpect to the <hi>Houſe:</hi> for when the Maſter being a Parent, Believed, there Salvation came to the Houſe, not ſo when only the Servant was Called, or did Believe; which is one Reaſon which the Apoſtle gives there, why a Brother or Siſter being married, ſhould not depart from, put away, or leave their Unbelieving Yoke-fellow, <hi>ver.</hi> 10, 11, 12, 13, 14. Not why the Converted Servant ſhould not leave his Uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted Maſter, <hi>ver.</hi> 20, 21, 22, 23.</p>
            <p>And this makes it more clear, That <hi>Houſe</hi> in the Scripture muſt include Infants, in that an <hi>Houſe</hi> is ſaid to be ſaved, (that is to ſay, ſaved as to the outward means of Salvation; which to them who die in their Infancy may be to their Eternal Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; howſoever will be ſo to them who ſurvive their Infancy, if they neglect not ſo great Salvation;) where the <hi>Parents</hi> are ſaid to be ſaved, but not <hi>Houſe</hi> ſaid to be ſaved without the <hi>Parents.</hi> Thus when <hi>Peter</hi> was ſent to <hi>Cornelius,</hi> Acts 11. it was to tell him words whereby <hi>He,</hi> and all his <hi>Houſe</hi> ſhould be ſaved: the ſame which <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Silas</hi> here ſaid to the <hi>Jailor,</hi> Act. 16. And ſo to every <hi>Parent, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve in the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and thou ſhalt be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and thy Houſe:</hi> which muſt be with reſpect to <hi>Infants;</hi> for as it would be hard to ſay, That <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants</hi> could not be of the <hi>Houſe</hi> which was to be ſaved; ſo it would have been needleſs to ſay, The <hi>Houſe</hi> was it, not for the <hi>Infants</hi> ſake. The Adult of every <hi>Houſe,</hi> if they Believed being ſaved, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:36641:11"/> the <hi>Parents</hi> did Believe or not; ſo that exclude <hi>Infants</hi> from being of the <hi>Houſe,</hi> and it makes all thoſe grants of Salvation made to the <hi>Houſe</hi> upon the <hi>Parents</hi> believing; ſuch as that to <hi>Zacheus, Luke</hi> 19.9. <hi>This day Salvation is come to this Houſe, foraſmuch as he alſo is a Son of Abraham.</hi> And here to the <hi>Jailor, Believe in the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and thou ſhalt be ſaved, and thy Houſe,</hi> to be ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluous, and inſignificant: for the Adult of every <hi>Houſe,</hi> as is ſaid before, were ſaved, if they did Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, though the <hi>Parents</hi> believed not, nor were ſaved; but no <hi>Houſe</hi> is ſaid to be ſaved without the <hi>Parents.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> But when it is ſaid, <hi>Believe in the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and thou ſhalt be ſaved, and thy Houſe:</hi> The meaning is, Thou thy ſelf believing, ſhalt be ſaved, and thy Houſe, if they believe; and ſo reſpects only the Adult.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> This cannot be the whole meaning, both becauſe no <hi>Houſe</hi> is ſaid to be ſaved without the <hi>Parents;</hi> and becauſe this excludes <hi>Infants</hi> from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſaid here to be ſaved, as well as from being ſaid to believe: When therefore it is ſaid, <hi>Believe in the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and thou ſhalt be ſaved, and thy Houſe.</hi> It is meant of ſome benefit (that is, to be ſaved) that ſhall redound to the Houſe by the Parents profeſſing to believe; which would not have redounded to it, if the Parents did not make the profeſſion, which muſt have reſpect prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally to the Infant Children, which the Parents have, or ſhall have afterwards. <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.7, 8.</p>
            <p>Add unto this, that the <hi>Houſe</hi> was always bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed, when the <hi>Parents</hi> were baptized, but not <hi>Houſe</hi> without the <hi>Parents.</hi> Thus it is, <hi>Lydia,</hi>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:36641:12"/> and her Houſhold, the Jailor and all His, and <hi>Criſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus</hi> with all his Houſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ceſar</hi> and his Houſhold were not baptized, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſome of his Servants were ſo, whereas <hi>Lydia</hi> and <hi>Stephanas</hi> ſtanding in a nearer relation to theirs, they being baptized, their Houſe and Houſhold were baptized alſo, and ſo all other Houſes ſaid, or that may be ſaid to be baptized; if the Parents, their Houſholds, but no Houſhold without the Parents, though <hi>Parent</hi> is ſometimes mentioned, and not the <hi>Houſe,</hi> and ſometimes the Houſe, and not the Parent, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.15, 16. Now if when any Parents were baptized, their Houſe, Houſhold, and all theirs were baptized, unleſs any of the Adult refuſed for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; and no Houſe or Houſhold were baptized, where one or both the Parents were not ſo, it neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarily ſuppoſeth ſome Infants baptized in thoſe bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed Families, ſince they that were of Age therein, who were baptized, were baptized upon their own account.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> But ſome may object; Firſt, that Houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold and Houſe are not always ſaid to be baptized with Parents; it is not expreſly ſaid, <hi>Acts</hi> 18.8. that the Houſe of <hi>Criſpus</hi> was baptized; nor doth the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.15. reckon it amongſt thoſe whom he enumerates to have baptized there; ſo nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is it expreſly ſaid of the Houſe of <hi>Cornelius,</hi> that it was baptized.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Be it ſo; yet ſo long as it is ſaid of <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nelius,</hi> that he feared God with all his Houſe, <hi>Acts</hi> 10.2. and had Words ſent unto him, whereby he and all his Houſe ſhould be ſaved, <hi>Acts</hi> 11.14. and of <hi>Criſpus,</hi> That <hi>he believed in the Lord with all his Houſe:</hi> And that <hi>Criſpus</hi> and <hi>Cornelius</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:36641:12"/> were baptized; it is all one as if it had been expreſly ſaid, that all their Houſe were baptized with them. Nay further, though it be not expreſly ſaid of <hi>Zaccheus,</hi> and that Noble-Man, <hi>John</hi> 4.53. that they were baptized, yet nothing can be more evident; for though Chriſt baptized not, yet his Diſciples did, and that as a great part of their Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment during Chriſt's Abode with them, for they baptized more than <hi>John, John</hi> 4.1. Now they baptizing ſo many, who ſhould they baptize, if not them? and if them, why not their Houſe and Houſholds? For if others thus and ſo qualified were baptized, themſelves and theirs, themſelves and all their Houſe, why not theſe, being qualified after the ſame manner, baptized, they, themſelves and theirs, themſelves and all their Houſe?</p>
            <p>Which that they were, is ſufficiently confirmed by this, That though it be not expreſly ſaid in any of the Goſpels, that the Diſciples of Chriſt bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed any particular Perſons or Houſholds; yet when we come to the Acts of the Apoſtles, by whoſe proceeding then we may ſee what was their Practice all along before then, as alſo 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.15. we have a clear and particular account not only of the bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizing of ſingle Perſons, but alſo of the baptizing with Parents, their Houſe and Houſholds. And this was always taken for granted, elſe we can aſſign no reaſon why the Apoſtle inſtancing in the baptizing of <hi>Criſpus</hi> in the aforecited 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.15. names him ſingly, and mentions not his Houſe; and may be one reaſon why the Apoſtle there ſaith, that he was not ſent to baptize, but to preach the Goſpel; name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, becauſe that if he had baptized all that he had converted, eſpecially where Parents and Houſholds
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:36641:13"/> were concerned, it would have hindred his preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: But as Chriſt taught, and his Diſciples bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed, ſo the Apoſtles might preach, and others under them ſometimes baptize thoſe whom they had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted. Thus it was at <hi>Corinth,</hi> when many of the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> hearing <hi>Paul,</hi> believed: and ſo we may ſuppoſe at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> upon <hi>Peter</hi>'s Sermon, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.41.</p>
            <p>And it is to be obſerved that when the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> gives us the names but of three which he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred he had baptized of thoſe many <hi>Corinthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> who are ſaid to believe, <hi>Acts</hi> 18.8. that of two of them, to wit, <hi>Criſpus</hi> and <hi>Stephanas,</hi> it is expreſly ſaid, Them and their Houſe; for though in the <hi>Corinthians</hi> it is ſingly <hi>Criſpus,</hi> as is obſerved before, yet in the <hi>Acts</hi> it is <hi>Criſpus</hi> with all his Houſe; and if <hi>Gaius</hi> was <hi>Gaius the Hoſt,</hi> which ſuppoſes an Houſhold, and <hi>Gaius Paul</hi>'s Hoſt, which ſuppoſes a baptized Houſhold, then the ſame may be ſaid of him alſo.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> 2. But <hi>Houſe</hi> and <hi>Houſhold</hi> is not always an Hebraiſm, for Children, eſpecially Infant-Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren; for 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 16.15. it is ſaid, <hi>Ye know the Houſe of</hi> Stephanas, <hi>that it is the firſt-Fruits of</hi> Achaia, <hi>and that they have addicted themſelves to to the Miniſtry of the Saints:</hi> Now Infants could not do this.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Put <hi>Houſe</hi> and <hi>Parents</hi> here aſunder, and then none of the Houſe could be Infants; but as In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants joined with Parents, are ſaid, <hi>Jer.</hi> 35. to be the Houſe, and to be ſpoken to, <hi>ver.</hi> 2. to anſwer, <hi>ver.</hi> 6. and to obey, perform and do, <hi>ver.</hi> 8, 10, 14, 16, 18. ſo Infants may be ſaid to be of the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:36641:13"/> Houſe of <hi>Stephanas,</hi> who addicted themſelves to the Miniſtry of the Saints.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> 3. But it is ſaid, <hi>John</hi> 4.1. <hi>That Chriſt made and baptized more Diſciples than</hi> John; now <hi>made</hi> ſeems to imply only Adult.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> If by <hi>Diſciples</hi> here be meant only thoſe who did baptize, for Chriſt baptized not, but his Diſciples, (that is, one another firſt, and then o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers) then they could be none but Adult; but if by Diſciples be meant alſo (as it muſt) thoſe who were baptized, then it comprehends thoſe <hi>all Men</hi> ſaid to come unto Chriſt, <hi>John</hi> 3.26. ſuch as thoſe Multitudes, <hi>Mat.</hi> 14.13 to 22. amongſt whom many were Children.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> 4. But it is ſaid, <hi>Acts</hi> 8.12. <hi>They were baptized, both Men and Women.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> None can reſtrain theſe words, <hi>Men and Women,</hi> to Perſons of ſuch an exact Age; neither becauſe it is ſaid, <hi>Men and Women,</hi> doth it hinder Infants from being underſtood alſo, any more than that ſaying, <hi>Nehem.</hi> 8.3. Ezra <hi>read the Law to the Men and Women, and to all that could hear with <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding,</hi> doth hinder that their little ones were ſome of the Aſſembly, which that it did not, is cleared before in <hi>page</hi> 14, 15. When therefore it is ſaid Men and Women, the Senſe is not, that none but of ſuch an Age, were or may be baptized, but that there was no diſtinction of Sex in Baptiſm,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.28.</note> as there had been in Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion; for this, and that the things concerning the Kingdom of God were preached to them, <hi>ver.</hi> 12. being <hi>Samaritans;</hi> and that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by Salvation came to their Houſes, and that of ſuch was the Kingdom of God, it was that there was
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:36641:14"/> great Joy in the City, <hi>ver.</hi> 8. And it being <hi>Criſpus</hi> ſingly in the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> which in the <hi>Acts</hi> is <hi>Criſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus</hi> with all his Houſe, it is a further Confirmation of this Senſe, ſince Infants may as well be couch'd under the terms of Men and Women, as <hi>Criſpus</hi>'s Houſhold under his Name.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> 5. But what if there were no Infant-Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren in the Houſholds of <hi>Lydia,</hi> of the Jailor, and of <hi>Criſpus,</hi> how then could there be Infant-Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren there baptized?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> If there were no Infant-Children in the Houſholds of <hi>Lydia,</hi> of the Jailor, and of <hi>Criſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus,</hi> they could not be baptized: but then this Obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction ſeems to grant, that if there were, they were baptized: Now that there were Infant-Children in thoſe Houſholds, (and none dare ſay there were not) appears from theſe following Conſiderations.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That <hi>Houſe, Houſhold,</hi> and <hi>His,</hi> (which are the Words here uſed) are, as proved before, when ſpoken of Perſons, an Hebraiſm, ſo common and familiar to expreſs Children by, whether Infants or Adult, that there is none more frequent and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That ſuppoſe theſe Houſholds to be without Infant-Children, and one may as well ſuppoſe all the Houſes and Houſholds, whoſe Parents were bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed in thoſe times, which could not be few, to be without Infant-Children, which is a thing not to be ſuppoſed.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That an Houſe being ſaid to believe, to be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and to be baptized, where the Parents are ſaid to believe, to be ſaved, and to be baptized, and no Houſe ſaid to believe, to be ſaved, and to be bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed, but whoſe Parents are ſaid to believe, to be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:36641:14"/> and to be baptized, it muſt be with reſpect to their Children, eſpecially their Infant-Children, the Adult being to make Profeſſion for themſelves.</p>
            <p>And it being not only the Apoſtles <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Paul,</hi> but all the Diſciples and Apoſtles of Chriſt who they baptized, that is to ſay, with Parents, their Houſe and Houſhold, and no Houſe and Houſhold without the Parents, there can be nothing more plain, than that it was the Apoſtolical Practice in baptizing Parents and their Houſholds, to baptize their Babes and Infants.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> 6. But when Chriſt renewed his Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion for baptizing, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.19. he mentioned not Infants.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> He then mentioned Infants as much as Adult, for he mentioned neither of them expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> 7. But we have freſh Examples of Adult Perſons being baptized, not ſo of Infants.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> The expreſs Examples of thoſe whom the Diſciples and Apoſtles of Chriſt baptized, are of two forts; the One of particular Adult Perſons, the Other of Parents and their Houſe, (for a Man and his Houſe is Parent and Houſe) which being not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Parents and Adult, but Parent and Infants alſo, and as to Baptiſm eſpecially Infants, as is made good all along before; the baptizing of <hi>Lydia,</hi> the Jailor, <hi>Criſpus,</hi> and the like, and their Houſe in conjunction with them, affords us as expreſs Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the baptizing of Infants, as of the baptizing of any Adult therein, and conſequently as of the baptizing of any other adult Perſons whatſoever.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> 8. But Chriſt was not baptized in his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fancy, and he knew when rightly to be baptized.</p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:36641:15"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> This makes nothing againſt the baptizing of Infants; for as there were none then to baptize him; ſo his Baptiſm being in order to his Miniſtry, into which he was not to enter by the Law (which he came to fulfil, <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.17.) till his being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout thirty years of Age; he was not to be bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed till he had accompliſhed that Age. Beſides, it is a Queſtion whether the Baptiſm by <hi>John</hi> the Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt, and the Baptiſm of Chriſt by his Diſciples and Apoſtles, were one and the ſame: for tho there be much ſaid for it, and many Inſtances of Parallels drawn whereby they are made to ſeem ſo, yet if it belonged unto Chriſt miniſterially to inſtitute and ordain the Sacraments of the New Teſtament, and if he could not miniſterially do that till he was duly ordained and admitted into the Function and Office of his publick Miniſtry, which was not till his Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm by <hi>John,</hi> then <hi>John</hi>'s Baptiſm could not be a Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel-Sacrament, and if not a Goſpel-Sacrament, then his, and Chriſt's Baptiſm, though they might agree in many other things, could not be one and the ſame.</p>
            <p>Now as Chriſt's not being baptized in his Infan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy is no Argument againſt the baptizing of Infants: ſo his Baptiſm, and the Baptiſm of <hi>John</hi> not being one and the ſame, makes the Name of <hi>Baptiſt</hi> an improper diſtinction for ſuch as profeſs the Baptiſm of Chriſt; as alſo that though the Diſciples of Chriſt, who had Commiſſion from him to baptize, baptized thoſe among themſelves into the Baptiſm of Chriſt, who before had been baptized into the Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm of <hi>John,</hi> as appears clearly by comparing <hi>John</hi> 1.35, 37, 40, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> with <hi>John</hi> 4.1, 2. and than which there is no clearer Proof of their being baptized at all; yet the rebaptizing of any now is altogether ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs and unwarrantable.</p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:36641:15"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> 9. But what benefit of Baptiſm are In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants capable of more, than they are capable of the benefit of the Lord's-table? are they not as capable to receive a ſmall quantity of Bread and Wine, as to be Baptized?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> This is to arraign the Inſtitutions of God, the profit of which, namely, That of Circumciſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which included Infants, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.12. The Apoſtle reſolves to be <hi>much every way, chiefly, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe unto them were committed the Oracles of God, Rom.</hi> 3.1, 2. It arraigns alſo the Commands of God mentioned before, <hi>Deut.</hi> 31.11, 12, 13. <hi>Joel</hi> 2.12. And the expreſs practice of the Apoſtles, who when they baptized <hi>Parents,</hi> baptized their <hi>Houſe,</hi> and <hi>Houſhold;</hi> not ſo when they adminiſtred to them the Lord's Supper, it being not there, <hi>a man and his Houſe,</hi> but, <hi>let a Man examine Himſelf.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> 10. But Churches by means of <hi>Poedo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſm</hi> become unholy, and unholieſt.</p>
            <p>If Churches become Unholy by means of <hi>Paedo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſm,</hi> then by what means did the Primitive Churches become unholy, with all that unholineſs that is charged upon them in the ſeveral Epiſtles directed to them before, and in the Revelations, if it was by means of Paedobaptiſm, then Paedo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſm was in uſe in thoſe times; if it was not by means of Paedobaptiſm, then Churches may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come unholy by ſome other means. And if Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry does not wrong the Churches of the Antipoedo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſts, they have not been ſo holy as they ſhould have been: Now by what means came they to be unholy, and unholieſt? As for ſuch who being bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized in their Infancy do not anſwer the Profeſſion of Faith and of a good Conſcience, whereinto they
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:36641:16"/> were baptized, but do afterwards make Shipwrack of that Profeſſion, and perſiſt therein: <hi>it had been better for them not to have known the Way of Righteouſneſs, than after they have known it, to turn from the holy Commandment once delivered to them;</hi> but is no argument, why none but Adult Perſons ſhould be baptized, for theſe alſo may make defection, unleſs we will confute all experience; and then what way or courſe may, or ought to be taken with them upon this occaſion, the ſame may be taken with others upon the like, and ſo Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity and Holineſs be preſerved and ſecured in the Churches of God as much this way, as it is preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded it may be in the other.</p>
            <p>But there remains two things yet to be reſolved; in reſolving of which it will be proved, That Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, and Parents only, where they may be had, have right to preſent their Children unto God in Baptiſm.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt.</hi> 1. The Firſt, how do Infants covenant, and engage to be God's People, or take Chriſt to be their Lord in Baptiſm?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> By their Parents, who having firſt given their own ſelves unto the Lord, are bound to give and dedicate their Children, both Infants and Adult, as their Seed unto him alſo: And for this cauſe it was, that no Houſe was baptized without the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents; the Adult covenanting and engaging for themſelves, and the Parents for the Infants; Parents doing of which for their Infants, being as <hi>Joſhua,</hi> reſolving that <hi>he</hi> and his <hi>Houſe</hi> would ſerve the Lord, whilſt the Infants promiſing by their Parents, is as we may ſo ſay, as <hi>Levies</hi> paying Tithes in the Loins of <hi>Abraham.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:36641:16"/>
            <p>And tho' that may be verified of Infants, when their Parents covenant for them in Baptiſm, which Chriſt ſaid to <hi>Peter, What I do thou knoweſt not now.</hi> Yet this can be no bar to this practice, that Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, <hi>(but thou ſhalt know hereafter)</hi> being as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicable to them, as it was to him.</p>
            <p>And truly, they who go about to diſpute them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves and others out of Infant-baptiſm by ſuch like Arguments, ſaying, <q>How do Infants know that their Parents covenant for them? And how can any after Infancy tell what engagement lies upon them thereby?</q> may as well ſay, How do we know who was the Father that begat us, or the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that brought us forth? and ſo caſt off that great Commandment with Promiſe, <hi>Honour thy Father, and thy Mother.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt.</hi> 2. The ſecond is, Why then are not Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, but others required in their ſtead, to anſwer for their Children in Baptiſm?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Some have thought, that the requiring of Others, inſtead of the Parents, to anſwer for their Children in Baptiſm, was not brought into a Canon, till the Clergy was prohibited Marriage, and it may be ſo. But waving that the uſual anſwer is, That however Parents might be chiefly concern'd in this at the firſt, yet becauſe Parents might be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away by Death, driven away by Perſecution, or by ſome other means neceſſarily detain'd, when their Children were to be baptized, the Church might require that Others ſhould appear for them; by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring of which, the Church doth not exclude any Title which the Children have by the right of the Parents: for the Sponſors may be ſuppoſed to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear in a threefold capacity. Firſt, as repreſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:36641:17"/> the Parents in offering up the Children unto Baptiſm, and thereby challenging in their Right. Secondly, by repreſenting the Children in the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers that are made in Baptiſm. Thirdly, in their own capacity, when they promiſe to take care of the good Education of the Children in the Principles of the Chriſtian Faith.</p>
            <p>But tho' this may be done in defect of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, yet that Parents when they may be had, ſhould be quite juſtled out by theſe, who were taken in only to ſupply their defects, ſeems not only to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dervalue, but oppoſe the Wiſdom of the firſt times, and doth too much reſemble the ſetting light by <hi>Father and Mother,</hi> complain'd of <hi>Ezek.</hi> 22.7.</p>
            <p>And whereas it is fairly pretended, that tho' one of the reaſons (to wit, the Perſecution of thoſe Times) which made Sureties more neceſſary in the firſt Ages of the Chriſtian Church, hath long ſince ceaſed; yet that they are continued for good ends, as (not only to offer up, repreſent and promiſe, but) to covenant on the Childrens behalf, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure the Church that they may be brought to Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation, and own their Covenant hereafter.</p>
            <p>Theſe are Reaſons why there ſhould be ſome Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties for Infants; but none at all, why Others ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than the Parents, but altogether on the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; for Parents are not only much more reſponſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for all thoſe good ends, but are confeſſedly thoſe who were chiefly made uſe of in the firſt Ages of the Chriſtian Church, till the Perſecution of thoſe Times cut them off. Now if Perſecution was one main thing that afterwards hindred Parents, and that it was a Perſecution ſo to do; why it ſhould be thought a thing expedient in it ſelf to
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:36641:17"/> hinder them now, by ſtill requiring Others in their ſtead, the reaſon ceaſing, is very difficult to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve.</p>
            <p>Nor is it ſo eaſy and ſmall a matter to be Sponſor, or Surety in this Caſe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccl.</hi> 5.2. to the 8th.</note> as many it may be make it to be; nor a Charge to be taken ſo raſhly, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiderately, as we may fear is done by the moſt. What Parents may do for their own Children, who are taken into Covenant with them, is one thing; and what they may do for the Children of Others, who ſtand not in that relation with them, is ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Every Chriſtian is obliged more or leſs, if not as a Witneſs, yet as a Monitor, to help each other in their Faith and Manners; but for any to Covenant with God, to Promiſe and Vow in the preſence of God, and of his People ſolemnly aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, to be ſuch or ſuch an one's particular Chriſtian Monitor, and in their own capacity to promiſe as a Surety, to take care of their good Education in the Principles of the Chriſtian Faith, not being their Parents, or where the Parents may be had, is a thing of an higher nature, and not without abſolute ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity, to be either required, or undertaken.</p>
            <p>And though the uſe of Sureties ſhould be ſo early in the Chriſtian Church, as ſome pretend, that it is not eaſy to fix the time of its beginning; or, that it ſhould be ſo ancient, as ſome think, among the <hi>Jews;</hi> as the time of <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> who took unto himſelf Witneſſes to record, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 8.2.</p>
            <p>Yet what are Sureties? The time of whoſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning it is not eaſy to fix, to thoſe made uſe of from the beginning. Or what are Witneſſes to Sureties? Were Witneſſes anciently Sureties? Or
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:36641:18"/> muſt we uſe Sureties, becauſe the Prophet took un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to himſelf Witneſſes?</p>
            <p>And as to the Reaſon of the thing: Is it to offer up, dedicate, and devote Children unto God, (by their Miniſtry, whoſe Office it is) and repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent them in Anſwers to be made in Baptiſm? Who are more proper for theſe than the Parents, whoſe they are, who are Parties with them, and who muſt anſwer in ſome reſpects to God for them?</p>
            <p>Is it to Promiſe, Vow, and Covenant on their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half? Who are more fit for this than the Parents themſelves, with whom the Covenant is made for themſelves and theirs, and without which, Sureties, and all their promiſing, vowing, and covenanting would ſignify nothing; Children having no right to Baptiſm, from the promiſing, vowing, and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venanting of Others; for ſo the Children of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidels might have right, but as the Parents them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves promiſe, vow, and covenant for them: And if other Sureties do challenge but upon the Parents right, why may not the Parents themſelves chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge upon their own?</p>
            <p>Is it to undertake for the Childrens good Educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the Principles of the Chriſtian Faith? who are laid under ſuch ſtrict Commands, bound in ſuch indiſpenſible Obligati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſa.</hi> 78.5, 6. <hi>Prov.</hi> 19.18. and 29.27.</note> charged with that care, and truſt, and furniſhed with thoſe fair and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantagious opportunities for the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge thereof, as the Parents? Doth not even Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture it ſelf teach us? And unto whom hath God ſaid at any time concerning the Children of Others, as unto Parents concerning theirs, <hi>Thou ſhalt teach them diligently unto thy Children, and ſhalt talk
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:36641:18"/> of them when thou ſitteſt in thy Houſe, and when thou walkeſt by the way, and when thou lieſt down, and when thou riſeſt up,</hi> Deut. 6.7. And when the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Ye Fathers, provoke not your Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren to wrath; but bring them up in the nurture and admonition of the Lord,</hi> Eph. 6.4. Of whom prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally ſaith he this, of the Fathers of their Fleſh, or of ſome others?</p>
            <p>And for the ſecurity of the Church, that the Children may be brought to Confirmation, and own their Covenant; Wherein are the Parents leſs re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſponſible, or more inſufficient than the Sureties? It is the Parents that God looks after; and if they bring up their Children for him, do they not bring them up for the Church? What needs the Church then any other Sureties? Or, wherein is it better ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by them? As for Sureties, it is well known, that any are generally accepted of: beſides, ſome do but ſtand for other Sureties; and ſome are Sureties for the Children of ſeveral Families: And what more common, than for the younger ſort of Sureties, to be removed into other Habitations and Abodes? And for thoſe of greater years, to have Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of their own, ſufficient to take up all their care and endeavours? Moreover, are not Families very often flitting, and changing their Dwellings? How then, it may be again asked, Is the Church more or better ſecured by Sureties, than it would be by Parents? whoſe Security, was it taken, would be ſomething; whereas that of Sureities is, beſides the uncertainty of it, uſually but in complement, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a Form of Godlineſs, but little or nothing of the Power of it; ſo that if it ſhould be demanded, What advantage, as to theſe things, hath the Church?
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:36641:19"/> Or, what profit is there by them unto the Parents, or their Children? Or, what Glory unto God? it would be hard to ſay, <hi>Much every way.</hi> Beſides, is not Filthineſs and Uncleanneſs hereby covered and masked? which it may be hoped would be ſhamed out, if Parents only were required perſonally to preſent their Infants.</p>
            <p>To ſum up All: Are any proper and compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to repreſent the Children of others, to offer them up in Baptiſm unto God, to promiſe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in for their vertuous and religious Education, to covenant with God for them, ſecure the Church, and receive the Charge and Exhortation given in their behalf? and muſt they not be much more proper and competent for their own? Or, if they be not proper and competent for their Own, how come they to be proper and competent for the Children of Others?</p>
            <p>Yet this hinders not, but that Others may hand Children from the Parents to the Miniſter; or ſtand as Witneſſes of their Baptiſm; ſo they proceed not to ſerve in things appertaining to the Parents.</p>
            <p>For the Service and Worſhip of God requiring perſonal Attendance, and it not being in the power of any to require the performance of one Man's Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Duty of another; or of one Man, to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form another Man's Religious Duty for him. So that if any ſhould require One man to go to the Church, ſerve God, partake of the Lord's Supper for another; Or, if any ſhould pretend that he doth all theſe things, by another's doing it for him, it would be nothing. Even ſo to offer up, devote, and dedicate Children unto God in Baptiſm, to Covenant for them, and therein ſolemnly to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:36641:19"/> and vow the Religious Education of them, all which are part of the Chriſtian Religion, and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Worſhip, is no diſcharge to the Parents, whoſe Part and Duty it is, let them pretend what they will of doing it by others, unleſs they themſelves do per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form it. And therefore that Parents ſhould be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired and neceſſitated to do it by others, or it muſt not be done at all, when they themſelves may do it, is a matter that deſerves the moſt ſerious conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of thoſe who challenge not a diſpenſing or infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Power.</p>
            <p>If any ſhould think that Parents therefore may not anſwer, promiſe, vow or covenant for their Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren in Baptiſm, becauſe this would be to ſerve God for them.</p>
            <p>It follows not: For when Parents anſwer, promiſe, vow and covenant in their Childrens Name, they do not perform their Childrens Duty for them, but thereby engage them to it, and perform their own: And ſo far as the Parents Act of giving up, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicating their Children unto God in a way of Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, and therein anſwering for them, is a Work of Neceſſity and Mercy, it is no more a performing of their Childrens Duty, or a ſerving of God for them, than praying to God for them, or being their Mouth to God in Praiſe, is.</p>
            <p>To conclude; Since Suretiſhip, and making Vows for others, is no light and eaſy matter; that this for Children, being in things of the greateſt moment, and unto God who will not be mocked, is none of the meaneſt; and that it is not in our Power to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute one for another, or others in our ſtead to ſerve God for us, nor ſafe to trifle with ſacred things: how well would it be if that Suretiſhip, which is
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:36641:20"/> founded upon Covenant-Right, accommodated with the greateſt Advantages, moſt expedient in it ſelf, moſt competent for all the good Ends of Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſhip, moſt unqueſtionable, and which was from the beginning, to wit the Parental, was always re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired; unto the diſcharge of which, if ſuch, whoſe Miniſterial Calling and Emploiment it is, would ſuperadd their Endeavours by a frequent aſſiſting of the Parents upon all convenient Occaſions, remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring them always, that <hi>he is not a Chriſtian which is one outwardly,</hi> (Rom. 2.28, 29.) <hi>neither is that Baptiſm which is outward in the Fleſh; but he is a Chriſtian which is one inwardly, and Baptiſm is that of the Heart in the Spirit, and not in the Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, whoſe Praiſe is not of Men, but of God:</hi> How uſeful might this be, and more religious, than for them, waving the Parents, to bind heavy Burdens and grievous to be born, and lay them on other Mens Shoulders, and they themſelves not move them with one of their Fingers?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Now the God of Patience and Conſolation grant us to be like-minded one towards another, according to Chriſt Jeſus; that we may with one Mind and one Mouth glorify God, even the Father of our Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt;</hi> Rom. 15.5, 6.</p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="appendix">
            <pb facs="tcp:36641:20"/>
            <head>An Appendix.</head>
            <p>AS to Chriſt his being baptized when 30 Years Old, at the beginning of his Miniſtry, (men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned here <hi>pag.</hi> 26.) and alſo about the Differences and Agreements of Chriſt his Baptiſm and <hi>John's,</hi> let the inquiſitive Reader peruſe and pauſe upon thoſe brief, but excellent touches hereupon, which that diligent Reader of the Sacred Scriptures, Mr. <hi>Samuel Clark,</hi> hath lately given us, in his Notes on <hi>Matth.</hi> III. 6, 16. Tho I confeſs that Chriſt's Plea for his being baptized by <hi>John, [Thus it becomes us to fulfil all Righteouſneſs]</hi> I cannot yet ſay that I underſtand it in its utmoſt reach and force to my full ſatisfaction. That Chriſt was bound to (and ſo muſt) fulfil the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and <hi>John</hi>'s Prophetic Miſſion, and the whole Law of Mediation which his Father laid him under, and he ſo voluntarily obliged himſelf unto, admits no Doubt, and needs no Proof: But what particular Law Chriſt here reſpected as to this Inſtance, I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſay I yet fully know.</p>
            <p>As to <hi>Sponſors,</hi> (God-fathers and God-mothers) 1. Let them be ſerious, and devoted Perſons unto God and Chriſt, themſelves. 2. Capable of Receiving, and likely and willing to fulfil this Truſt. And, 3. then appear and ſtand as the Subſtitutes and Repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives of Abſent Parents through Neceſſity; or Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parents, where Parents are dead, or manifeſtly give their Children wholly to them; or, as in Conjuncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Concurrence with the Parents, for the more
<pb facs="tcp:36641:21" rendition="simple:additions"/> effectual Chriſtian Education of the baptized Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren. And then leſs may be ſaid againſt them, and more for them than otherwiſe. And then their Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony will be more credible, that Perſons offering their Seed to God, are ſuch as very probably have a right thereto. That the Perſons offered are bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized; and that in caſe the Parents die, or deny the Faith, or prove groſly negligent as to the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of their Truſt, care will yet be taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the fit Chriſtian Education of their baptized Seed. But why Parents (where they can) ſhould not Solemnly and Perſonally offer their own natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Seed to God, and perſonally profeſs and promiſe, I know not: Seeing this renews their Chriſtian Profeſſion, reinforces their Chriſtian Obligations and Advantages upon themſelves; hands down the Eſſentials of Chriſtianity from Age to Age; calls other Parents to reflect upon themſelves as to their Chriſtian Advantages, Performances, and Concerns; and quickens all the Baptized to their Work and Hope. I will not vouch for every Word and Thing in this, or any meer humane Book; but I think it no loſt time or labour to read this ſmall Tract.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>M. S.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:36641:21"/>
            <head>Mr. <hi>Joſeph Whiſton</hi> hath publiſhed theſe Treatiſes about this Subject, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </head>
            <list>
               <item>1. INfant Baptiſm from Heaven, and not of Men; or a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate Diſcourſe concerning the Baptiſm of the Infant-Seed of Believers.</item>
               <item>2. Infant-Baptiſm from Heaven, and not of Men, the 2d Part: Or, an Anſwer to Mr. <hi>Danvers</hi>'s Treatiſe of Baptiſm. Wherein Infants Right to Baptiſm is further confirmed.</item>
               <item>3. An Eſſay to revive the Primitive Doctrine and Practice of Infant-Baptiſm, in the Reſolution of Four Queſtions. 1. What are the Reaſons of God's appointing the Token of his Covenant to be applied to the Infant-Seed of his People. 2. What is the Good or Benefit they receive thereby. 3. What is the Duty of Parents towards their Children, as bearing the Token of the Covenant. 4. What is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement that Children, as grown up to Years of M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>rity, may and ought to make of the Token as applied to them in their Infancy.</item>
               <item>4. Infant-Baptiſm plainly proved. A Diſcourſe wherein certain Select Arguments for Infant-Baptiſm, formerly ſyllo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtically handled, are now abbreviated, and reduced to a plain Method for the Benefit of the Unlearned. With a large Epiſtle to the Pious and Learned among the <hi>Antipaedobaptiſts,</hi> eſpecially the Authors of the late Confeſſion of their Faith.</item>
               <item>5. A brief Diſcourſe concerning Man's natural proneneſs to, and tenaciouſneſs of Errors. Whereunto are added, ſome Arguments to prove, That that Covenant entred with <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> Gen. 2.7. is the Covenant of Grace.</item>
               <item>6. The Right Method for the proving of Infant-Baptiſm. With ſome Reflections on ſome late <hi>Tracts</hi> againſt Infant-Baptiſm.</item>
            </list>
            <p>All ſold by <hi>Jonathan Robinſon</hi> at the Golden-Lion in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-Tard. Together with ſeveral other Treatiſes in Defence of Infant-Baptiſm, by <hi>Mr.</hi> Baxter, Mr. <hi>Wills,</hi> Mr. <hi>Barret,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:36641:22"/>
            <head>
               <hi>An</hi> ADVERTISEMENT. <date>
                  <hi>Decemb.</hi> 2. 1689.</date>
            </head>
            <p>THere is newly Publiſhed, <hi>A Large Folio Bible of a fair new Roman Letter,</hi> with Annotati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and Parallel Scriptures or References (ſome Thouſands more than are in the <hi>Cambridg, Oxford,</hi> or any <hi>London</hi> Bibles yet extant.) To which is an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed, The Harmony of the Goſpels: As alſo a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction of the Jewiſh Weights, Coins, and Meaſures, t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> our Engliſh Standard: And a Table of the Promiſes in Scripture.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By Mr.</hi> SAMUEL CLARK.</p>
            <p>In <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>e entire Volume, containing Three hundred twenty five Sheets in Good Demy Paper.</p>
            <p>Propoſed By th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Bookſellers undermentioned on theſe Terms, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>I. He that Buys only one Book, to pay Twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty five Shillings Unbound.</item>
               <item>II. He that Buys Six Books, ſhall have a Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth <hi>Gratis,</hi> which reduces the Price to a Guinea Unbound.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Which Terms are to continue until the Firſt of <hi>May</hi> next: But after that, no Seventh Book will be allowed, nor a ſingle Book Sold under Twenty ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven Shillings Unbound.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Richard Chiſwel</hi> and <hi>Jonathan Robinſon</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-yard.</p>
            <p>And by <hi>Brabazon Aylmer</hi> in <hi>Cornhill.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:36641:22"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
